<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-17T09:50:18+00:00</updated><id>https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to avoid prompt injection attack by following prompt engineering best practices?</title><link href="https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/prompt-injection-attack/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to avoid prompt injection attack by following prompt engineering best practices?"/><published>2023-07-11T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-11T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/prompt-injection-attack</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/prompt-injection-attack/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[using language models in production comes with its own risks. Read the article to learn how to mitigate them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GPUs: Why you can never have enough?</title><link href="https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/GPUs-substack-article/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GPUs: Why you can never have enough?"/><published>2023-04-28T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-28T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/GPUs-substack-article</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/GPUs-substack-article/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[the real reason why GPUs are in demand and why it's not going to stop]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Context Revolution: Taking machines beyond algorithm</title><link href="https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/Context-Revolution/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Context Revolution: Taking machines beyond algorithm"/><published>2023-02-07T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-07T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/Context-Revolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://satpreetmakhija.github.io/blog/2023/Context-Revolution/"><![CDATA[<p>The computation revolution started when we built general purpose computers to follow instructions. A computer follows an algorithm step by step. It doesn’t need to <i>understand</i> the algorithm.</p> <p>Here’s an example to illustrate the difference between <i>understanding</i> something and following an algorithm. There’s a world renowned chef, Andre, who makes a special pasta dish. Andre lost both his arms (sorry Andre). He hires you to make this dish. You don’t know anything about how to make this dish. You don’t know these ingredients, how they taste, which ones blend together. But, Andre is great at communication. He gives you step by step procedure to make the dish and you follow along with him. Voila! You made the special pasta only Andre knows how to make. Andre <i>understands</i> how to make this special pasta. You followed an algorithm. But what is it that Andre has that you don’t? Context. He knows the flavour of the ingredients, he knows what they taste like, he knows which ingredients complement each other and which don’t. He has context around the algorithm. This context is what I proxy for as understanding.</p> <p>The AI revolution is about giving computers more context around the computation they perform.</p> <p>“Write me a function to add five numbers.” - you give the prompt to a language model that runs on a computer. The computer doesn’t have an algorithm to give you the output you want. It only knows how to execute an algorithm. The language model contains the context to make head and tails of the prompt. We will provide this context to computers via AI such as natural language, our physical reality, our visual imagery, anything and everything we have access to. With time they will have as much context as we do. This is what I call the Context Revolution.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[how AI changes computations performed by a computer]]></summary></entry></feed>